Finding Aid for Sally Lusk Papers, 1975-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sally Lusk papers 1975-2001
Lusk, Sally.
4 linear feet
0667 Aa 2
Sally Lusk was a professor of nursing at the University of Michigan from 1969 to 2003. She was very involved in the field of occupational health nursing, and focused her research on the effects of noise on workers, as well as how to integrate nursing research into practice. The collection mainly consists of conference presentations, papers, and grant projects related to her research.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection (donor #9218) was received in June and August, 2002. NO.
The collection is open without restriction.
Sally Clark Lechlitner Lusk, PhD, RN, FAAN, graduated from Memorial Hospital School of Nursing in 1961, and received her Bachelor of Science in Nursing from Indiana University in 1967. She received a Masters of Public Health from the University of Michigan in 1969, and a PhD of Educational Psychology from the University of Michigan in 1979. She is mainly involved with the field of occupational health nursing.
Sally Lusk worked as a nurse in various locations from 1961 to 1968 before becoming an instructor at the University of Michigan School of Nursing in 1969. She became an Association Professor of Nursing, with tenure, in July 1973, and Professor of Nursing in September 1995. She also became Director of Occupational Health Nursing in 1987.
Lusk's main research interests are the role of nurses and the effect of noise. She has conducting many studies on noise-induced hearing loss in factory and construction workers, non-auditory effects of the noise, and means to improve the use of hearing protection among workers. Lusk has also been involved in studying the role of occupational health nurses in the corporate and industrial environments, how nurses can use nursing research to improve their practice, and on protecting health care workers from blood-born pathogens.
In addition to her research, Sally Lusk has been instrumental in improving nursing education in Michigan. In the late 1970's, she headed an effort to design a community-based Bachelor of Science in Nursing program for registered nurses. Programs were established at three off-campus locations to allow nurses to continue their education while working. She was also involved in starting the Masters in Occupational Health Nursing at the University of Michigan, improving University of Michigan Nursing curriculum, and establishing an on-campus masters program in occupational health nursing for working nurses.
Sally Lusk retired in 2003.
For additional information, see her website at http://www-personal.umich.edu/~lusk/
This collection is divided into 5 series: Personal, Conference Presentations, Grant Projects, Publications and Other Activities.
Acronyms frequently used in this collection:
AAOHN -- American Association of Occupational Health Nurses
AHCPR -- Agency for Health Care Policy and Research
APHA -- American Public Health Association
BSN -- Bachelor of Science in Nursing
COHSE -- Center for Occupational Health and Safety Engineering, (University of Michigan)
HEMA -- Health Education Media Association
MNRS -- Midwest Nursing Research Society
Subjects:
American Association of Occupational Health Nurses.; Agency for Health Care Policy and Research.; American Public Health Association.; Health Education Media Association.; Midwest Nursing Research Society.; Lusk, Sally.
- Personal
  Personal (0.1 linear feet) contains several curriculum vitae from different points in Lusk's career, as well as a summary of her proposed activities for a sabbatical leave from 1995 to 1996 and a taped interview with Lusk. Social security numbers have been redacted from the CV's.
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1)
  - "News Briefs Interview With Sally Lusk," (audio cassette tape) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Sabbatical Leave 1995-1996 (Box 1)
- Conference Presentations 1988-1997
  Conference Presentations (1.25 linear feet, 1988-1997) includes abstracts, presentation slides, notes, handouts, and summaries of data from presentations given by Sally Lusk. The main topics covered are the effects of noise on factory workers, using nursing research to improve nursing practice, and the role of occupational health nurses. There is also a list of presentations given by Sally Lusk from 1976-1997. The papers are arranged in reverse-chronological order.
  - List of Presentations 1976-1997 (Box 1)
  - Psychosocial Factors Influencing Use of Hearing Protection by Factory Workers and Construction Workers November 1996 (Box 1)
  - Noise Annoyance Among Factory and Construction Workers: Construct Development (MNRS) April 1996 (Box 1)
  - Noise Annoyance Among Factory and Construction Workers: Construct Development, March 1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Noise Annoyance Among Factory and Construction Workers, (includes color photographs of worksite and color slides of hearing protection in use) November 1995 (Box 1)
  - Use of Hearing Protection Equipment by Factory Employees and Construction Workers November 1995 (Box 1)
  - Non-Auditory Effects of Noise (APHA Abstracts) November 1995 (Box 1)
  - Factors Influencing Use of Hearing Protection in Four Samples of Workers (APHA) October 1995 (Box 1)
  - Use of Hearing Protection by Factory Employees and Construction Workers (APHA) October 1995 (Box 1)
  - Preventing Noise-Induced Hearing Loss (APHA) October 1995 (Box 1)
  - Non-Auditory Effects of Noise (APHA) October 1995 (Box 1)
  - Worksite Health Promotion Programs July 1995 (Box 1)
  - Motivating Management and Employees to Prevent Noise-Induced Hearing Loss, (includes 3.5" floppy disk of NHCA HPD rating systems templates) March 1995 (Box 1)
  - An Empirical Base for Interventions to Promote Use of Hearing Protection in Construction Workers (MNRS) 1995 (Box 1)
  - Pilot Test of a Training Program to Increase Blue Collar Workers' Use of Hearing Protection (MNRS Intervention Paper) April 1994 (Box 1)
  - Partnerships in Nursing Research: Impact on Practice, Service and Policy April 1994 (Box 1)
  - Non-Auditory Effects of Noise as a Stressor: A Synthesis of Research (poster) November 1993 (Box 1)
  - Explaining Workers' Use of Hearing Protection: a Test of a Causal Model November 1993 (Box 1)
  - An Empirical Base for Interventions to Promote use of Hearing Protection October 1993 (Box 1)
  - Preventing Noise-Induced Hearing Loss in Construction Workers July 1993 (Box 1)
  - Differences in Workers' Lifestyles: Implications for Planning Health Programs (AAOHN Poster) April 1993 (Box 1)
  - Nursing Research and Its Multidisciplinary Dimensions March 1993 (Box 1)
  - Test of the Health Promotion Model to Predict Use of Hearing Protection March 1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Health-Promoting Lifestyle for Blue Collar, Skilled Trade and White Collar Workers (AJHP Conference) February 1993 (Box 1)
  - Conference on Research Priorities in Nursing Science November 1992 (Box 1)
  - Non-Auditory Effects of Noise as a Stressor November 1992 (Box 1)
  - Comparison of Lifestyle for Blue Collar, Skilled Trades, and White Collar Workers November 1992 (Box 1)
  - Test of a Causal Model to Explain Use of Hearing Protection (APHA poster) October 1992 (Box 1)
  - Lifestyles of Blue Collar, Skilled Trade and White Collar Workers (APHA poster) March 1992 (Box 1)
  - Lifestyles for Blue Collar, Skilled Trades, and White Collar Workers March 1992 (Box 1)
  - Use of Hearing Protection: Predictors from the Health Promotion Model October 1991 (Box 1)
  - Use of Hearing Protection: Predictors from the Health Promotion Model (MNRS Poster) April 1991 (Box 1)
  - Health Promotion in the Worksite and in the Community January 1991 (Box 1)
  - Psychosocial Stressor for Nurses' Aides November 1990 (Box 1)
  - Predictors of Health-Care Workers Use of Gloves with Low Risk Patients May 1990 (Box 1)
  - SPH Presentation (notes and diagrams on health promotion in businesses) 1989 (Box 1)
  - Health Protecting Behavior and the Health Promotion Model 1989 (Box 1)
  - Nurses' Role in Industry: Current and Future June 1989 (Box 1)
  - Health Protecting Behaviors and the Health Promotion Model April 1988 (Box 2)
  - Regional Hearing on National Health Objectives for the Year 2000, March 1988 (Box 2)
  - Future Roles for Nurses in Industry October 1987 (Box 2)
  - Issues in Health Promotion Research April 1987 (Box 2)
  - Corporate Demand for Occupational Health Nursing: Implications for Practice and Education (APHA Presentation) September 1986 (Box 2)
  - Survey of Forbes 500 Corporations Regarding Occupational Health Nursing April 1986 (Box 2)
  - Demand by Major Corporations for Nursing Services November 1985 (Box 2)
  - OHN Presentation February 1985 (Box 2)
  - Beliefs Regarding the Poor and Performance in Community Health Nursing January 1983 (Box 2)
  - Open-Mindedness and Performance in Community Health Nursing January 1983 (Box 2)
  - Stereotypes-Community Health Nursing April 1982 (Box 2)
  - Attitudes and Students' Public Health Nursing Performance October 1980 (Box 2)
- Grant Projects 1974-2000
  Grant Projects (1.75 linear feet, 1974-2000) is composed of papers related to several grant projects that Sally Lusk directed. Most of the papers are from starting a community-based Bachelor of Science in Nursing program for registered nurses in the 1970s. Papers include grant applications, progress reports, and workbooks developed for the program. The other grant projects are from the 1990s and include developing an interactive computer program to educate workers on the use of hearing protection, studies on worker hearing loss, and establishing an on-campus masters program in occupational health nursing for working nurses. The papers are arranged alphabetically by grant. Social security numbers have been redacted from the grant applications.
  - A Community-Based BSN Program for Registered Nurses
    - First Grant Application 1974 (Box 2)
    - Grant Continuation Proposal 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Grant Continuation Proposal 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Program Publicity 1976-1978, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Progress Reports 1978 (Box 2)
    - Project Budget 1977-1980 (Box 2)
    - Workbooks
      - Family and Community Health Nursing (Box 2)
      - Management for Nursing (Box 2)
      - Nursing Intervention in the Care of the Adult (Box 2)
      - Nutrition in Health Care (Box 2)
      - Parent-Child Nursing (Box 3)
      - Pharmacology and Therapeutics (Box 3)
      - Professional Nursing Matrix (Box 3)
      - Psychiatric-Mental Health Nursing (Box 3)
  - Effectiveness of a Computer-Based Tailored Intervention to Increase Use of Hearing Protection
    - Script Draft 1996 (Box 3)
    - Final Script 1998 (Box 3)
    - "Interactive Video: Bio Medical" (VHS) 1997 (Box 3)
    - Presentations 2000 (Box 3)
    - Results Summaries and Analysis, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Factors Influencing Health Care Workers' Use of Protection to Prevent Exposure to AIDS 1991 (Box 3)
  - Non-Auditory Effects of Noise (UAW-General Motors) 1991 (Box 3)
  - Nursing Model to Reducing Noise-Induced Hearing Loss
    - Proposal 1992 (Box 3)
    - Progress Report 1993 (Box 3)
    - Application 1992-1995 (Box 3)
    - Final Report 1994 (Box 3)
  - On Job/On Campus (OJOC) Master's Program-Public Health Nursing and Occupational Health Nursing
    - Proposal Draft (Box 3)
    - Grant Proposal 1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Publications 1988-1997
  Publications (0.25 linear feet, 1988-1997) contains copies of articles published by Sally Lusk, mostly on the role of nurses and the effects of noise on workers. Many of the articles are from a series she wrote for the American Association of Occupation Health Nurses Journal entitled "Linking Practice and Research." A few articles also include notes from peer reviews. The articles are arranged in reverse-chronological order.
  - Core Curriculum for Occupational Health Nursing, Chapter 3, AAOHN 1997 (Box 3)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: Health Complaints of Older Workers," AAOHN Journal September 1997 (Box 3)
  - "Noise Exposure: Effects on Hearing and Prevention of Noise Induced Hearing Loss," AAOHN Journal August 1997 (Box 3)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: Health Effects of Stress Management in the Worksite," AAOHN Journal March 1997 (Box 3)
  - "Gender Differences in Blue Collar Workers' Use of Hearing Protection," Women & Health 1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - "The Health Promotion Model as a Causal Model of Construction Workers' Use of Hearing Protection, Research in Nursing & Health," Research in Nursing & Health 1996 (Box 3)
  - "Using Incentives to Promote Workers; Participation in Worksite Research," Psychological Reports 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: Worksite Health Promotion and Disease Prevention Studies," AAOHN Journal December 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: Enhancing Compliance with Universal Precautions," AAOHN Journal September 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: Research, Do We Need It?," AAOHN Journal June 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Test of the Health Promotion Model as a Causal Model of Workers' Use of Hearing Protection," Nursing Research, May /June 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Conducting Worksite Research: Methodological Issues and Suggest Approaches," AAOHN Journal April 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: HIV Educational Interventions with Low Risk Groups," AAOHN Journal March 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Preventing Noise-Induced Hearing Loss," AAOHN Update V 1993 (Box 4)
  - "Predicting Use of Hearing Protection: A Preliminary Study," Public Health Nursing 1993 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: Job Stress," AAOHN Journal December 1993 (Box 4)
  - "Predictors of Workers' Use of Hearing Protection: Implications for Training Programs," Public Health Nursing September 1993 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research," AAOHN Journal June 1993 (Box 4)
  - "Preventing Noise-Induced Hearing Loss," AAOHN Update Series May 1993 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research: AAOHN Journal March 1993 (Box 4)
  - "Noise Exposure," MAOHN Newsletter January 1993 (Box 4)
  - Letter to the Editor, Journal of Nursing Education 1992 (Box 4)
  - "Linking Practice and Research," AAOHN Journal December 1992 (Box 4)
  - "Selling Health Promotion Program Recommendations for Occupational Health Nurses," AAOHN Journal September 1992 (Box 4)
  - Editorial: "Violence in the Workplace," AAOHN Journal May 1992 (Box 4)
  - "Violence Experienced by Nurses' Aides in Nursing Homes," AAOHN Journal May 1992 (Box 4)
  - "Health Care Workers Use of Gloves," Infection Control and Hospital Epidemiology 1991 (Box 4)
  - Letter to the Editor: "Personal Control and Health Promotion," Social Science Medicine 1990 (Box 4)
  - "Corporate Expectations for Occupational Nurses' Activities," AAOHN Journal August 1990 (Box 4)
  - "Interest of Major Corporations in Expanded Practice of Occupational Health Nurses," Research in Nursing and Health 1988 (Box 4)
- Other Activities
  Other Activities (0.25 linear feet) are papers from organizations Lusk was involved in related to nursing. These include the Agency for Health Care Policy and Research (AHCPR) Nurse Scholar Program and Workers Health Expert Meetings (1998-2000), the Health Education Media Association (HEMA) Board (1976-1979), and curriculum development for the University of Michigan Nursing Program (1998).
  - Agency for Health Care Policy and Research (AHCPR) Nurse Scholar Program
    - Program Description 1998 (Box 4)
    - Role of Nurses and Nursing Research 1998-2000 (Box 4)
    - Workers Compensation Health Care Project 2000 (Box 4)
  - AHCPR Workers Health Expert Meetings 2000, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Center for Occupational Health and Safety Engineering (COHSE) (Box 4)
  - Health Education Media Association (HEMA)
    - Correspondence 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Meeting Minutes 1976-1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Publications 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan School of Nursing
    - Proposal for Master's Degree Program in Occupational Health Nursing (Box 4)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Revision 1998 (Box 4)